<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Silencer | YuanSilencer</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/tag/silencer/</link><atom:link href="https://yuansilencer.com/tag/silencer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Silencer</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://yuansilencer.com/media/icon_hu_7613a4a452ac7087.png</url><title>Silencer</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/tag/silencer/</link></image><item><title>An oligodendrocyte silencer element underlies the pathogenic impact of lamin B1 structural variants</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/post/25-05-08-3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yuansilencer.com/post/25-05-08-3/</guid><description>&lt;p>A non-coding &lt;strong>silencer&lt;/strong> near &lt;strong>LMNB1&lt;/strong> constrains lamin B1 expression specifically in &lt;strong>oligodendrocytes&lt;/strong> via &lt;strong>CTCF‑mediated looping&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>PRC2&lt;/strong> recruitment. Loss of this element—through upstream deletions or tandem duplications—drives overexpression and explains the tissue‑specific pathology of &lt;strong>autosomal dominant leukodystrophy (ADLD)&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract-concise-summary">Abstract (concise summary)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Investigating families with &lt;strong>LMNB1&lt;/strong> tandem duplications that surprisingly &lt;strong>do not&lt;/strong> show demyelination, alongside ADLD tissues, CRISPR‑edited cell lines, and mouse models,
the authors identify an &lt;strong>oligodendrocyte‑specific silencer&lt;/strong>. This element contains &lt;strong>CTCF&lt;/strong> sites that form &lt;strong>3D chromatin loops&lt;/strong> and recruit &lt;strong>PRC2&lt;/strong>, reducing LMNB1 transcription
in oligodendrocytes. &lt;strong>Loss of the silencer&lt;/strong> (by upstream deletion) or &lt;strong>functional uncoupling&lt;/strong> (with certain duplications) elevates LMNB1 expression and underpins ADLD’s
&lt;strong>cell‑type specificity&lt;/strong> and pathogenesis.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways">Key takeaways&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mechanism&lt;/strong>: CTCF‑anchored looping plus &lt;strong>PRC2‑mediated repression&lt;/strong> keeps LMNB1 low in oligodendrocytes; removing the element lifts repression.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Evidence&lt;/strong>: Multi‑family human genetics, ATAC/ChIP, CRISPR editing, reporter assays, RNA/protein readouts, and &lt;strong>mouse models&lt;/strong> converge on the same mechanism.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Clinical lens&lt;/strong>: Explains why LMNB1 dosage changes cause &lt;strong>CNS‑restricted demyelination&lt;/strong>, despite broad LMNB1 expression.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Therapeutic angle&lt;/strong>: Restoring the silencer’s function (synthetic silencers/insulators, epigenetic targeting) could normalize LMNB1 in ADLD.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="suggested-citation">Suggested citation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Nmezi B, Rodriguez Bey G, DeFrancesco Oranburg T, &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> &lt;strong>An oligodendrocyte silencer element underlies the pathogenic impact of lamin B1 structural variants.&lt;/strong>
&lt;em>Nat Commun.&lt;/em> 2025;16(1):1373. doi:10.1038/s41467-025-56378-9.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Identification of RNA-binding protein hnRNP C targeting the 3′UTR of the TAP-associated glycoprotein tapasin in melanoma</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/publication/2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yuansilencer.com/publication/2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Melanoma cells exploit &lt;strong>hnRNP C&lt;/strong> to bind a repressive site in &lt;strong>tapasin (TAPBP)&lt;/strong> 3′UTR, lowering HLA‑I antigen presentation. Genetic/biochemical disruption of this interaction restores tapasin and boosts HLA‑I surface levels—implicating hnRNP C as a biomarker and target for T‑cell–based immunotherapy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract-concise-paraphrased">Abstract (concise, paraphrased)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The study identifies &lt;strong>hnRNP C&lt;/strong> as an RNA‑binding protein that recognizes a &lt;strong>silencer motif&lt;/strong> within the &lt;strong>TAPBP (tapasin)&lt;/strong> 3′UTR in melanoma.
By binding this site, hnRNP C decreases tapasin expression and limits &lt;strong>HLA class I&lt;/strong> antigen processing and presentation.
Across cell models and patient‑derived materials, loss or inhibition of hnRNP C increases &lt;strong>TAPBP mRNA/protein&lt;/strong> and elevates &lt;strong>HLA‑I&lt;/strong> at the cell surface.
These findings position hnRNP C as a regulator of tumor immune visibility and a potential &lt;strong>therapeutic/diagnostic handle&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways">Key takeaways&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mechanism&lt;/strong>: hnRNP C engages a &lt;strong>3′UTR silencer&lt;/strong> in &lt;em>TAPBP&lt;/em>, dampening antigen processing and &lt;strong>HLA‑I&lt;/strong> display.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Evidence&lt;/strong>: RNA‑protein assays, reporter constructs, perturbation genetics, and analyses of melanoma samples converge on the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Impact&lt;/strong>: Relieving this repression could enhance &lt;strong>T‑cell recognition&lt;/strong>, offering a route to improve immunotherapy responsiveness.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="suggested-citation">Suggested citation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Wang Y, Lazaridou M‑F, Kordaß T, &lt;strong>et al.&lt;/strong> &lt;em>Identification of RNA‑binding protein hnRNP C targeting the 3′UTR of the TAP‑associated glycoprotein tapasin in melanoma.&lt;/em> &lt;strong>OncoImmunology.&lt;/strong> 2024;13(1):2370928. doi:10.1080/2162402X.2024.2370928.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Intragenic viral silencer element regulates HTLV-1 latency via RUNX complex recruitment</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/post/25-05-08-viral-silencer-element/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yuansilencer.com/post/25-05-08-viral-silencer-element/</guid><description>&lt;p>An intragenic &lt;strong>viral silencer&lt;/strong> within the HTLV‑1 provirus recruits the host &lt;strong>RUNX&lt;/strong> complex to dampen sense‑strand transcription and promote latency. Disrupting this element boosts HTLV‑1 expression and immunogenicity; inserting it into HIV‑1 suppresses production—revealing a portable, cis‑acting latency switch.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract-concise-summary">Abstract (concise summary)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The study maps an &lt;strong>open chromatin region&lt;/strong> inside the HTLV‑1 provirus that functions as a &lt;strong>silencer&lt;/strong> of the 5′‑LTR. The element binds &lt;strong>RUNX1/CBFβ&lt;/strong>, limits transcriptional bursts and antigen expression, and thereby supports &lt;strong>viral persistence&lt;/strong>. &lt;strong>CRISPR mutagenesis&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>reporter assays&lt;/strong> show that removing the element elevates viral transcripts and replication, while &lt;strong>heterologous insertion&lt;/strong> into HIV‑1 diminishes virion output. These results uncover a host‑factor‑tethered &lt;strong>intragenic latency module&lt;/strong> with therapeutic implications for retroviral control.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways">Key takeaways&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mechanism&lt;/strong>: RUNX complex binding to an intragenic silencer represses HTLV‑1 sense transcription and stabilizes latency.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Portability&lt;/strong>: The element is sufficient to suppress HIV‑1 production when transplanted into the HIV‑1 genome.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Methods&lt;/strong>: ATAC‑seq, luciferase reporters, CRISPR editing, qPCR/ddPCR, ChIP‑PCR, flow cytometry and patient PBMC analyses.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Why it matters&lt;/strong>: Identifies a discrete, druggable node for &lt;strong>latency control&lt;/strong> that could inform antivirals or vaccine‑adjuvant strategies.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="suggested-citation">Suggested citation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Sugata K, Rahman A, Niimura K, &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Intragenic viral silencer element regulates HTLV‑1 latency via RUNX complex recruitment.&lt;/strong> &lt;em>Nat Microbiol.&lt;/em> 2025;10(6):1447–1462. doi:10.1038/s41564-025-02006-7.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Unraveling an enhancer-silencer regulatory element showing epistatic interaction with a variant that escaped genome-wide association studies</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/post/25-05-08-enhancer-silencer/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yuansilencer.com/post/25-05-08-enhancer-silencer/</guid><description>&lt;p>A dual-function cis-regulatory element (“ESpromoter”) can act as both enhancer and silencer to tune ATP2B4 and LAX1 in human T cells; its allele-specific interaction with rs11240391 helps explain severe malaria risk.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract-concise-summary">Abstract (concise summary)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The authors identify an &lt;strong>enhancer–silencer promoter (ESpromoter)&lt;/strong> that &lt;strong>activates ATP2B4&lt;/strong> yet &lt;strong>represses LAX1&lt;/strong> in single human T cells. Using integrative genomics,
CRISPR perturbations, reporter assays, and cohort genetics, they show an &lt;strong>epistatic interaction&lt;/strong> between five ESpromoter SNPs and &lt;strong>rs11240391&lt;/strong> in the LAX1 promoter.
This allele-specific interaction reduces &lt;strong>LAX1&lt;/strong> expression and associates with &lt;strong>severe malaria&lt;/strong> susceptibility, challenging the classic enhancer–silencer dichotomy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways">Key takeaways&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dual-function regulatory DNA&lt;/strong>: one element can enhance one gene (ATP2B4) while silencing another (LAX1) within the same cell context.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mechanistic link&lt;/strong>: the LAX1 promoter variant &lt;strong>rs11240391&lt;/strong> (FOS::JUN binding site) modifies the repression strength exerted by the ESpromoter.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Evidence stack&lt;/strong>: chromatin interaction maps, CRISPR deletions, RT-qPCR, luciferase reporters, and human cohort genetics support the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Disease relevance&lt;/strong>: allele-specific regulation contributes to &lt;strong>severe malaria&lt;/strong> risk via &lt;strong>T-cell activation&lt;/strong> pathways.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="citation">Citation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Adjemout M, Nisar S, Escandell A, et al. &lt;em>Unraveling an enhancer-silencer regulatory element showing epistatic interaction with a variant that escaped genome-wide association studies.&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Cell Genomics&lt;/strong>. 2025;5(7):100889. doi:10.1016/j.xgen.2025.100889.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: This post contains a &lt;strong>paraphrased&lt;/strong> summary and metadata only. For the official full text and figures, visit the PMC link above.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Unconventional microRNA role: Enhancing the human leukocyte antigen class I antigen processing pathway via interacting with a silencer</title><link>https://yuansilencer.com/publication/unconventional-microrna-role-enhancing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yuansilencer.com/publication/unconventional-microrna-role-enhancing/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="notes">Notes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>PMID: &lt;code>39439221&lt;/code> • PMCID: &lt;code>PMC11496566&lt;/code> • DOI: &lt;code>10.1002/ctm2.70010&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Journal: &lt;em>Clinical and Translational Medicine&lt;/em>, 14(10):e70010 (2024)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This post includes a &lt;strong>paraphrased&lt;/strong> abstract and key points for lab notes. For the official full text, see the PMC link above.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>